[music]
I'm Ashan Ratansi [music] and welcome
back to Going Underground broadcasting
all around the world including right
across India from the UAE. 14 years to
the day that the USA officially declared
its illegal invasion of Iraq over as it
continued to kill, wound or displace
countless Afghans for the next decade.
This was during a period when the world
now knows the CIA ran a global torture
program at so-called black sites. We
know about the torture program because
of the CIA's John Kiryaku who when he
blew the whistle was rewarded with a
prison sentence. This of course is the
CIA that is associated with countless
assassinations and anti-democratic
violence all around the world since it
was set up in 1947. Today, the CIA under
Trump's John Ratcliffe is intricately
involved in Gaza via links to Mossad in
Aman. In Ukraine, it trained Zalinski's
intel chief. And Venezuela, where Trump
has openly boasted of his authorization
of a CIA backed coup. John Kiryaku, a
veteran of counterterror in Bahrain,
Greece, Pakistan, and Langley, and the
State Department, now hosts the podcast
Deep Focus, and he joins me from
Washington, DC. John, thanks so much for
coming back. It's been quite a few years
since you've been on. I think going
underground was one of the first
programs when you came out of jail that
you came on. Now everyone wants to hear
from you. Why Why is it now Tucker
Carlson wants to hear from you and
different people want to hear from you
when you came on Going Underground what
nearly 10 years ago, nine years ago, no
one was interested in your story.
>> No. You know, it's funny. I I really
believed at the time that the country
would finally come around to my way of
thinking on this issue and it appears
that that's what what has happened.
Torture is wrong. It's wrong under any
circumstances. It's not patriotic. It's
a criminal act. And finally, a majority
of the American people agree with me.
>> So that's progress at least. I'm not
sure whether you caught our episode with
the former Tel Aviv uh CIA chief of
station Susan Miller. She was saying
that uh there's no way the CIA has been
involved in drug trafficking before I
reminded her about in Iran Contra.
Why does the CIA drug traffic and
continue to do so arguably? I mean
Candace Owens has now been talking about
it with respect to the Charlie Kirk
assassination. Why is the CIA intimately
involved with drug trafficking?
>> Because trafficking and drugs allows
them to get closer to the targets they
want to get closer to. There's a popular
Netflix uh television series called
Narcos. And Narcos is is based on the
true story of the hunt for Pablo
Escobar, the hunt for the Cali cartel,
the hunt for one of the Mexican cartels.
And over the course of three seasons,
every time the Drug Enforcement
Administration gets close to its primary
target, the CIA station chief steps in
and ruins the investigation.
That is true. That happens in real life
because the CIA doesn't care about
drugs. It cares about terrorism. It
cares about communism for what that's
worth. There's always some other bigger
ism that the CIA is concerned about. And
so it was perfectly happy to allow
cocaine to flood into the United States
in the 1980s during the Iran Contra
affair, just as it was perfectly happy
to allow Afghanistan to provide 93% of
the world's heroin once the United
States began its occupation of
Afghanistan.
>> Yeah. You said that the CIA was uh
intimately involved in spreading that uh
those drugs from Afghanistan. You know,
uh, you're quoting Netflix makes me
think of this Financial Times headline.
I can see which side you're on.
Paramount gate crashes Netflix deal for
Warner Brothers. Warner Brothers
associated with a chief propaganda
outlet CNN, of course. Um, how
important? I mean, you're you're on
Netflix's side there with that program
Naros, but I don't expect if they take
over Warner Brothers that CNN would
suddenly tell us about CIA covert ops.
How important uh does the CIA feel that
soft power through Hollywood, through
television programs, they've already got
the media captive arguably. How
important does the CIA see that as
important?
>> Critically important to the point where
the CIA has set up a branch within the
Office of Public Affairs whose job it is
solely to cooperate with Hollywood
studios. Just like the FBI has been
doing since the 1950s, the CIA works
with Hollywood Studios to make sure that
everything that comes out of Hollywood
has a pro-CIA message. You know,
technically it's illegal for the CIA to
propagandize the American people. But
that's what happens every time a CIA
related film is released. It's
propaganda. Indeed, the movie Zero Dark
30 broke all kinds of laws. the the
director Katherine Bigalow and the uh
writer Mark Bull were given classified
briefings over a classified mockup of
the Osama bin Laden compound. Uh they
were given classified briefings by CIA
counterterrorism center analysts and in
exchange they gave those analysts
watches and free tickets to the premiere
of the film. Well, they should all be in
prison for that. Technically that's a
violation of the Espionage Act. Instead,
the film was celebrated as a as a
victory at the CIA.
>> And we've seen how actors are now on a
blacklist if they've expressed support
for uh Palestine. Uh now,
>> that's right.
>> So that uh so that they can't work
again. But then, ironically, regarding
the Warner Brothers deal and uh all
related to Larry Ellison, of course, and
uh the Trump family, why do they need to
be so open about trying to take over the
corporate news when arguably the news
stations have all been paths for CIA
covert ops for decades since their
inception? Why are they why do they need
extra control? Is it the Gaza genocide
that has made them more aware?
I think that's probably a part of it,
but I I think the real reason is a
little bit more crass. Uh and that is
just uh billions and billions of dollars
in profits. Essentially, the entire
American media is run by six
corporations or oligarchs. Uh now it's
going to be five. And so the only place
you can go is independent media. But so
few Americans have the time or the
inclination to seek out independent
media. They just sit in front of the
television, turn on CNN or MSNBC, now
it's called MS Now or Fox News, and they
think they're being uh they're being
educated. In fact, they're not. They're
being propagandized.
>> And uh I suppose you'd say your new
podcast, Deep Focus, is going to set all
that straight to an extent. I mean,
Miller, as I say, Susan Miller, the
former CIA chief of Station, she does
did seem as outraged as I think you have
been about Trump's ambassador to Israel,
Mike Huckabe, inviting Jonathan Pollard
into your embassy in Israel. Clear that
uh clear that the United States knows
that there is no ceasefire. Why does the
media I mean here's a headline from the
Middle East from here in Dubai. No true
second phase while Israel continues
violations. It's bombing Lebanon. Israel
hit says bullet targets in Lebanon. So
so it says here in Gulf News in Dubai.
They know that. Why is it that they take
the line from Huckabe I suppose as the
representative in the Middle East that
there is a ceasefire at all?
I say at every opportunity in every
interview that I can get myself
scheduled on that there is no peace
deal. There is not even a ceasefire, at
least not a well-maintained one. Maybe
the Amiradis are happy. Maybe the
cutteries are happy, the Bahrainis, even
the Saudis, but the Palestinians
certainly are not happy because dozens
of them still continue to die every day.
and Israel continues to bomb southern
Lebanon as well as Syria, southwestern
Syria. Um, Mike Huckabe was a was a
popular governor of a small, lightly
populated state. He thinks that he's
still governor and that he can make
these decisions independently of the
State Department or the National
Security Council. He can't and he needs
to be reprimanded for not falling into
line. But more than that, I went on
Twitter and said that I believed quite
strongly Huckabe should be forced to
resign solely for inviting Jonathan Pard
uh to a private meeting in the American
embassy. Jonath Jonathan Pard is a
traitor to the United States. He has
called for the use of Israeli nuclear
weapons against the United States. He
has called on every American Jew with a
security clearance to spy for Israel
against the United States. And he's
fetted at the American embassy and
treated like a VIP visitor. I I was so
outraged that I thought when I first
read the report that it was it was a
joke, that somebody was just playing a
joke, but unfortunately it wasn't a
joke. and and for that serious
um violation of well not just protocol
but common sense Mike Huckabe should
resign.
>> Is Mike Huckabe a traitor to the United
States of America? And are there people
in the CIA do you think who uh want him
gone now?
>> My guess would be that everybody at the
CIA wants him gone for this? No, I don't
think he's a traitor against the United
States. And excuse me for being blunt. I
think he's an idiot and he just didn't
think that this was any big deal.
>> That's that's being kind. You're famous,
of course, for exposing US torture
programs. I mean, now that we get more
and more revelations of the way Israel
has been torturing Palestinians during
the genocide, it continues to torture
doctors in the Middle East. Was it
Mossad teaching the CIA or the CIA
teaching Mossad and Aman how to torture
uh people, how to break uh all uh all
four Geneva conventions, the article
three of the four Geneva Conventions,
>> as awful as it might sound, they were
two independent programs running
parallel with each other. Uh while the
while the CIA was was developing its own
torture program, I never saw an Israeli.
I never heard reference to an Israeli. I
never saw anything about Israelis in the
in the reporting cables. Uh what the
United States did was was that it
outsourced torture to two sick
psychologists, contract psychologists
who reverse engineered the US Air
Force's SER training so that they could
exert the most amount of pressure, the
most amount of force and pain frankly on
uh on prisoners. The Israelis
don't follow anybody's rules. The United
States did this dance back in 200 uh
late 2001 and early 2002 where they went
to the CIA general counsel, then they
went to the Justice Department's Office
of Legal Counsel, then they went to the
general counsel of the National Security
uh uh council and they at least
pretended that they needed legal cover
to allow themselves to do this. the the
Israelis just go in with guns blazing.
>> But so clear that the CIA knows that the
Israelis are torturing people. I mean,
Susan Miller said that the um chief of
station of CIA's office always knew that
they had to clear things with Mossad
before operating, which seems like a
bizarre relationship. So bizarrely, has
it become permissible, openly
permissible all these years after your
revelations of US torture during the
so-called war and terror?
You know, I'm I'm sorry to tell you that
my revelations had a great impact on
paper. Uh my revelations were what led
to passage of the McCain Feinstein
amendment that banned torture in the
United States. But it did nothing to put
pressure on our allies like Israel to
stop torture or to dial back the
torture. And I wouldn't be surprised at
all if another whistleblower were to
come out and say, "Well, yeah, we don't
torture, but we still render prisoners
to countries that do torture." And then
we pay subsidies to those countries
intelligence services to pri to provide
us with the information that the
prisoner uh finally gives. With Israel,
it's it's an even stranger relationship.
The United States does not spy on
Israel, period. It just does not. And it
operates in Israel only with the
permission of the Mossad. It's a very
strange relationship. It's not a
terribly friendly one. It's proper. It's
it's formal, but not friendly. And the
US does nothing inside Israel without
the Mossad's permission.
John Keryaku, I'll stop you there. More
from the CIA veteran and whistleblower
after this break.
Welcome back to Going Underground. I'm
still here with the CIA veteran and
whistleblower John Kiryaku. John, in
part one, at the end of part one, you
were talking about uh torture and the
relationship between the United States
and Israel. I don't know what we were to
expect from uh Donald Trump and what you
think of John Ratcliffe in particular
because lots of the MAGA base are saying
there's uh been no arrests for the
Russia collusion hoax, no arrests for
those trying to talk up January 6th, no
arrests for the Biden auto pen, no
arrests for uh obviously the Jeffrey
Epstein case, no arrests regarding the
COVID behavior of uh the government, the
Biden government and no arrest for uh uh
things like even the Hunter Biden
situation and the laptop. What What is
the Trump administration doing? And is
it a case of Donald Trump not being in
control of his administration and behind
the scenes the same old uh uh policy is
being enacted?
>> I I don't think so. I think what what
you just mentioned this this laundry
list of uh of issues of problems uh
points to the strength the power the
entrenchment of the deep state. Donald
Trump I think really wants to get to the
bottom of so many of these scandals that
took place under both the Biden
administration and the Obama
administration but
>> and and his and his administration
>> and his own and his own administration.
But for the most part, judges are
stopping him from going forward. I have
to agree with you that that the fact
that John Brennan has not been charged
with a crime is deeply disturbing to me.
It seems to me like it would be actually
rather easy to charge John Brennan, at
least with conspiracy,
maybe even sedicious conspiracy, which
is a very grave crime. But I think the
information is clear, the evidence is
clear that John Brennan tried to deny
the American people their choice for
president of the United States in 2016.
And he did it by pointing the finger at
Russia. He did it by by loudly
proclaiming proclaiming, excuse me, that
the Hunter Biden laptop was a Russian
disinformation operation. It was not. It
was Hunter Biden's laptop. He said so
himself. Um, so where are the charges?
If they can throw a charge at at former
FBI Director Comey, for example, even
though it's been dismissed, it should be
easy to file charges against John
Brennan. There's an old saying here in
the United States that a grand jury
would indict a bologn sandwich. Okay,
let the indictments come, then let him
defend himself. Indeed, that's what he
said about me. He wrote a he wrote a
letter to former uh Attorney General
Eric Holder saying, "Charge him with
espionage." Holder wrote a letter back
saying, "My people don't think he
committed espionage." And then Brennan
wrote back and said, "Charge him anyway
and make him defend himself. That's
exactly what they did to me." And then
on the day that I that I declared
bankruptcy, they dropped the espionage
charges. Well, I I was innocent of
espionage. He certainly appears to be
guilty of conspiracy. Where are the
charges?
>> Can you sue him with President Trump?
Then you should get on the phone to the
White House. You can do a joint case.
>> I'm I'm trying. Believe me. Believe me.
>> But but there are forces there perhaps.
I mean, symptomatic of this is uh I mean
the confusion in the so-called liberal
media there. Who is responsible for the
president's war off the coast of
Venezuela? this uh in the Ssberger's uh
New York Times clear that Rubio and
Ratcliffe have some kind of wing there
within the Trump administration
and uh Rubio is going to need something
more to uh get his uh invasion of
Venezuela through despite the um
reservations of the MAGA base. Uh is the
is it the case that there's there is
this separation in the Trump
administration? No indictment, no arrest
and jailing uh of uh Brennan and uh no
uh no America first policy.
>> It sure seems that way. And and what
you're describing is is really very much
a war within the Republican party. You
know, the neoconservatives who were who
were in charge during the George W. Bush
administration and who were personified
by John McCain and Lindsey Graham to a
lesser extent are making a comeback
right now. And Donald Trump seems to be
a little bit confused as to what exactly
he wants his legacy to be. Does he want
it to be the America first anti-forign
intervention uh policy that he's
espoused all these years or is he going
to go back to the George W. Bush let's
invade everybody policy? I've said many
times that if you want to know what
American military intentions are, watch
naval movements. This is something that
I learned at the CIA. We can yell and
scream and point the finger and tell
countries we're going to invade them,
but we're not unless we send enough
naval assets
[clears throat]
to um to cover what's needed in terms of
supply. aircraft carriers, an aircraft
carrier battle group, for example, it
has 11 support ships, battleships, troop
transports, supply ships, and of course,
the aircraft carrier itself is full of
fighter jets. So, if if the United
States is serious about doing something,
it's going to send an aircraft carrier
battle group. And indeed, what did it
do? It sent the USS Gerald R. Ford
aircraft carrier battle group to the
coast of Venezuela. So, which Donald
Trump are we going to see? Are we going
to see the America First
non-intervention Donald Trump or the
neocon Donald Trump? And the truth of
the matter is
we're not at war with Venezuela.
Venezuela hasn't done anything to us.
They haven't attacked us. These drugs
that we're supposedly destroying or
intercepting or whatever aren't even
meant uh for the United States. They're
meant for Western Europe. And they're
not Venezuelan drugs. Venezuela is the
trans shipment point for drugs coming
from Colombia, Peru, and Ecuador. So, I
just don't see why
this president especially is considering
a war of choice, but on par, you think
he's probably not. I mean, this is being
recorded uh beforehand, so there might
have been a invasion he could have
declared because he has that battle
group there. uh by the time this
interview is uh broadcast and certainly
uh one element of having that kind of
flirtatilla in place they can't be there
for very long without the the needing to
be resupplied by more ships. I mean what
why do you think what does the CIA think
do you think about why they've failed in
Latin America time after time after time
uh in uh of course in in Nicaragua and
uh and in Cuba and in so many other
countries in Latin America they have
failed to overthrow countries let alone
a country the size of Venezuela
>> for decades and it's because of this
belief at the CIA it's a very deeply
held belief that we are the good guys
and as soon as we cross that border,
people are going to throw flowers at us.
And of course, that's that's laughably
laughably wrong. There's no
understanding of history. There's no
understanding of the societies and the
cultures of these countries. They don't
want us there. And at the CIA, they just
don't understand. Now, in their defense,
the CIA is not a policy um agency. It's
a policy support agency. So, just like
with the invasion of Iraq, if the White
House says do it, you have to do it,
even if you're opposed to it on
philosophical grounds. But you're right,
the CIA, the American government in
general, just never seems to learn the
lesson of invasions gone bad. It's easy
to invade a country. It's easy to
overthrow its government. It's
exceedingly difficult to take care of
things the day after. And one thing
about Venezuela too, as I just said, it
would be easy to overthrow the
government. We've already
essentially told Maduro, "Just get on
your plane and run away. Go to Doha, go
to Havana, go to Moscow. Just get on the
plane and run away." The the president's
president Maduro, his private pilot said
just a few weeks ago that the CIA had
approached him to try to recruit him. So
in the event that Madora were to run
away, instead of landing in Havana, he
would land in Miami thinking it was
Havana and we could take him off the
plane and charge him with drug
trafficking. The president just a couple
of weeks ago went on national television
and said that he had signed a covert
action program. Let me tell you, there
is nothing that the CIA does that is
more highly classified than a covert
action program. This was the first time
in American history that a president
ever announced one as he was signing it.
The point being to put so much pressure
on Maduro that he just gets up and runs
away. So to overthrow him, what do you
need to do? You need to secure the
presidential palace. You need to take
over the radio and television stations.
You need to control the major
intersections in Karacas. But most
importantly, you need to have the
military on your side. And the
Venezuelan military is on the side of
President Maduro.
>> Yeah. And uh I mean they've tried
against Cuba. It's not even easy to
overthrow them, arguably. Let's get to
uh Europe. The CIA, according to the New
York Times, has 12 spy bases on the
Russian border. And of course, we know
the CIA trained the intelligence chief
of Zalinski.
Do you believe that John Radcliffe is uh
overseeing the intel for Zilinski
despite Trump saying he's this neutral
arbiter? Is the CIA completely under
effectively genocide Joe Biden's policy
and not the Trump administrations?
What's the CIA doing with its 12 spy
bases in Ukraine?
>> I think that Donald Trump genuinely
wants to see an end to this conflict. I
really do. But I think he also has been
convinced to keep all these CIA bases
open until a peace deal is signed. I
think Ratcliffe probably has lobbyed him
and probably quite hard not to hamstring
CIA operations until the deal is done
and we can withdraw CIA personnel.
>> What happens when Russian troops
overtake the bases? What happens when
they take the bases?
Well, we've always had a gentleman's
agreement with the uh the Russians that
we don't uh harm or interfere with their
people and they won't harm and interfere
with our people. You know, I remember
when re reading reports uh from the
murder of the CIA station chief in
Athens, uh Dick Welch on December 23rd,
1975, the very first cable that we
received was from Moscow. And it was the
KGB saying, "We promise it wasn't us."
When John F. Kennedy was killed on
November 22nd, 1963, the very first
message that the CIA received was from
the KGB saying, "We promise it wasn't
us." There's this gentleman's agreement
that has always been respected. So,
sure, they might overrun CIA bases and
they'll likely expel those CIA officers,
but I wouldn't expect much more. Yeah,
I'm not sure whether they're gentlemen,
but we're running out of time. And I
better ask you, when it comes to
lobbying President Trump in in the White
House, I mean, we had Ben Manashe, the
former Israeli intelligence translator,
saying that uh the ghost of Jeffrey
Epstein effectively is blackmailing
Trump. He does seem uh awfully uh angry
uh with Marjorie Taylor Green or
completely out of proportion on this
issue of the Epstein Files. What's your
take on why he's been so reluctant to
keep his promise to release unredacted
despite Congress's uh recent uh change
of mind the Epstein files?
>> I think that we had a hint of what the
truth was when Elon Musk said as he was
leaving government that Donald Trump was
all over his words all over the Epstein
files. And I think Trump probably didn't
think that he would be or didn't realize
that he was when he was making the
promise to release all of the unredacted
files. I have to tell you, I'm not
sanguin that we'll ever see these files
because this is not a partisan issue.
There are Democratic perverts just like
there are Republican perverts and there
are a lot of them in positions of very
uh important uh power. And so I think
that I think that they are going to work
together to kill this information, to
disappear the information. Marjgery
Taylor Green is right. Uh Donald Trump
said that he would release it. He should
release it. This is what the MAGA base
wanted. But I think Trump believes that
the MAGA base is more proTrump than they
are pro MAGA and that he could wait this
out and win it in the end. I don't think
we'll ever see this unredacted
information.
John Kiryaku, thank you.
>> Thank you. Good to see you.
>> That's it for the show. Our continued
condolences to those berieved by the UK
US EU armed genocide across Palestine.
We'll be back on Saturday with a brand
new episode. Until then, keep in touch
by all our social media if it's not
censored in your country and head to our
channel, Going Underground TV on
rumble.com to watch new and old episodes
of Going Underground. See you Saturday.